hey ladies this is going to be a video
that addresses good and bad form and
I've never seen anyone try to really
tackle this topic and I think it's a
source of confusion for a lot of you
women out there um and a lot of men as
well especially a lot of beginners so we
have this ideal form that we want people
to use strength coaches and
powerlifters uh powerlifters especially
are very nitpicky about form because
over time they've kind of learned what
builds the best squats the best bench
the best dead list but they also know
that not every two people live the same
way you know they don't not everyone
looks the same way because of
anthropometry some people have long
femur some people are short some people
are tall some people have long arms and
these things dramatically affect how
your form is going to
look however the confusing part is
probably for a lot lot of women is like
well if I can lift more weight doing it
this way why should I do it that way and
allow me to explain I train a lot of
women for example in the deadlift they
are actually like stronger doing the
straight leg deadlift and they are
regular deadlift the most weight they
can pull is like when they're like
this like this right here when their
hips are even with their shoulders and
they're stronger here than if they
actually get down like this so why would
they want to pull why would they want to
drop their hips low if they're weaker
that
way so let's first talk about why why do
people use different form well someone
with big giant quads and short femurs
he'll probably want to do Sumo deas and
stay very upright and use his quads to
lift you know he'll try to use his legs
to lift the de but a slender person with
long fur and not a lot of quad mess they
can't squat that weight up so they're
going to have higher
hips so form is necessarily going to
look different depending on the lifter
but there are certain things that are
kind of negotiable and some
non-negotiables
for example in the
squat all right some people will squat
down and be very upright like this you
know and they'll they'll almost have
like vertical torso and they'll lift
straight up especially Olympic lifters
especially when they wear their Olympic
shoes you'll watch them and they will be
like
this powered up other people fold like
an accordion they will sit back you know
and and their hips will shoot up first
and they'll turn it into a squat
morning all right so I was training a
woman last week her squats were like
this
this is how she looked she would look
good on her way down she'd get to here
and then her hips would shoot up like
this and then she would go like this so
it look like
this
well that's how she's strongest she does
it like that because her quads are much
weaker than her backs side so she leans
forward straightens out her legs and
turns it into a good morning utilizing
her hamstrings to a greater
degree now could she keep lifting like
that her whole life probably but so
that's one option to just get stronger
that
way
but a lot of times what people think is
that oh I I use that crappy form so I
need a special exercise to help me so um
she might be thinking paw squats would
help me or leg press or front
squats but really what it boils down to
is you have the lighten the load if you
want to fix doing squat mornings you
what you have to do is lighten the load
up and be diligent you've got to
reinforce you've got to change up the
pattern that you've already established
so what happens is what you need to do
is come down to the the
bottom okay do not let the hips shoot up
first like that you have to stay keep
the the trunk angle the same like this
come
on she she can do that with lad or
loow just like that what the second she
starts wanting to go like this like that
the set stops every rep has to be like
that and that's how you fix
that here's your current squat strength
doing it like a good
morning but doing it that way upright
she's a lot weaker theoretically over
time she'll build this up to be the same
strength as this way but I'm here to
tell you that doesn't always happen um
some people just they can't get big
quads or they have long femurs they're
never going to be a strong squatting
that way so can you just keep doing the
squat mornings yes you can but you might
get hurt one day you might get hurt
because it might get to a point
where you're coming
down and then you shoot up and you go
like this and then you're like and then
you round your back like
that so the reason why it's important to
care about quote unquote good form is
that it keeps you healthy over
time doing it the upright way uses more
active muscle you're lifting with your
legs your quad muscles your muscles are
holding everything tight the more you
lean round and bend the more you're
relying on ligaments and things like
that and passive muscles stretch and
that can lead to strain so it's always
good to use more muscle and use more
active and keep better form now with the
with squats another thing you'll see
people do is they don't want to stay out
like this and come up their knees want
to come like this and this they
typically can come down looking like
this and then as soon as they initiate
the concentric phase they'll go like
this and come in now a lot of people can
do this just fine over time they'll
squat will look like this they'll come
in a little bit and come back out so
they squat like this do they ever get
hurt most people don't but again it's a
slippery slope what if they get to a
point where they're going like
this and their knees are touching you
know that would be bad you could start
getting knee pain so that's why you want
to build good habits and you want the
knees to stay up like this you want to
build this pattern just like you don't
want you want the trunk to stay at a
consistent angle when you squat like
this you don't want the hips to shoot up
like this same with
deadlift now torso angle has to
vary some people with with short femurs
and shorter
people they line up for a spot and
they're like this they're like super
upright and their torso angle will be
like this it's crazy especially with the
Sumo de if you'll see guys that are
like like this and they're like straight
up tall people lanky people people with
long femur and short arms if you have
long femur and short arms you're going
to look like
like this when you de it you know
there's just no way around it but in
general you don't want the back to round
too much like this so even if your hips
are high you want to make sure you're at
least pulling tight okay and then when
you lift again you don't want those hips
to shoot
up so if
you pull yourself tight and you look
like this that's pretty high hips that's
fine when you lift you don't want that
more angle to change you don't want it
to go like
this like
that
so can you lift with a rounded posture I
do it I've done it my whole life when I
go heavy when I go heavy you'll see me
get into
position I take a deep breath I and then
I pull and you'll watch my back go like
this and then it comes off the ground
but I keep it right here I don't let
myself go to here
this is full spinal
flexion so I'm an advanced lifter who's
been lifting a lot of years and I know
that here's an arch here's full flexion
Arch full flexion I can keep it right
here if I go to here I get hurt so I
know I've learned how to master my body
a lot of people haven't done that they
don't have that control of their spinal
segments but the safest way is to keep
an arch so the best the most safest way
and the way you're using the most muscle
and not relying on the ligaments and
things like that is to set
up chest up drop the hips a little bit
hold tight and
then like
this so this way uh you're not letting
the hips shoot up you're not rounding
the
back so it all boils down to this is
your goal to lift the most weight
possible or is it to work your muscles
and look the best if your goals are
physique related then I suggest drop the
weight and make it look pretty make your
squats look like this you know what I
mean make your deadlift look like
this if you are a power lifter and you
compete most of your lifts in practice
should look good save the sloppy form
for the platform
you can build your strength being strict
and then allow for some more wiggle room
on the platform and especially your
warm-up sets so make your warmup sets
stricter and then maybe your top set of
the day you allow for some wiggle room
but keep a make a checks and balances
system for example film yourself if you
film yourself and you notice that your
butt is shooting up your squats or
deadlist or you round the hell out of
your low back or your knees are totally
coming
in how how much are you willing to let
it slide you should know that you
shouldn't just wing
it anyway I hope this video sheds some
light on a complicated
topic if you're physique related use
good form and less weight if you are a
powerlifter most of the time use good
form allow for some wiggle room with
your top set of the day and then on a
platform thank you for watching